The islands
have always been a mystery.
Since the beginning,
over 1500 years ago
when the first
Polynesians arrived.
Following the light of the
eastern star called Nanamua.
With only the stars to
guide them they sailed
2,000 miles in canoes to
migrate to the islands
and they believed that they
had finally found paradise.
But paradise is
an elusive thing.
As long as men exist.
But this time new
foreigners came.
Perhaps seeking this
elusive peace or bringing us
a new peace.
In 1820 the Thornton's
and Hiram Bingham
came to the islands to
bring us the good news.
Well, Reverend.
I hope it's what you expected.
It's more.
What are you looking
to do here with these savages?
They're people, Skipper Jack.
They're naked!
It's all right, dear.
Tell that to Captain Cook.
They were not warmly
received when they arrived
in the village.
Our people have long
memories and they remembered
the ghost of Captain Cook.
They also despised the whalers
who preyed upon our women.
All was not well.
What do you want with Olani?
I have a letter of
intent from Papua Akia
in Boston he arranged a meeting
for both myself and Chiefess.
We should go this is not safe.
They don't want us.
Leave them be, Kanoa
Ah.
I am Chiefess Kapiolani.
Ah, it's a pleasure to
finally meet you, Chiefess.
We didn't expect
you to be so young.
It is rank that matters here
in the islands, Reverend
Thornton, not age.
It is a pleasure to
meet all of you, come.
Makana, Kapu help them
with their luggage.
You have a beautiful country.
And you speak English so well.
The British
sailors taught us.
Starting with Captain
Cook's men 50 years ago.
Ah, uh-huh, well.
Henry,
don't provoke them.
The Chiefess has
everything under control, right?
They're gesturing
towards us and pointing.
Come,
come, stay with us.
We didn't know what
to make of these new visitors.
They were not like the others.
The whalers who only
wanted to drink rum
and possess our women.
These people were here
for something else
and it made all of us uneasy.
The woman you encountered
earlier in the village
who was alarming anyone,
that is Priestess Kanoa.
Yeah, I saw.
Not everyone is like her.
The gods are extremely
angry with us.
I don't believe in God.
Only believe in myself.
Yeah, we can
see that, Skipper.
The gods?
Yes, Pele, she is
god of the volcano.
It is she who shaped
the sacred land.
We fear her greatly.
Henry,
where are we going?
I'm so tired, I need to rest.
Why are you here?
We are
just here to help.
Are you
here to convert us?
No, only
God can do that.
Why are you here then?
To help, we want to
help you in anyway we can.
Why do foreigners always
think they can help?
You brought guns to
our islands, remember?
Hey, those guns are
here to protect you, too.
From what?
Other guns.
Is there
something wrong?
The
goddess is very angry.
War is prevalent.
Please correct me if I'm
wrong, but your goddess
is an angry goddess?
Pele is temperamental.
She devours the land.
She is a goddess of
citron, Halema'uma'u
along with her husband Lohiahu.
It was when Lohiahu
kissed another woman,
her own sister, that
she covered him in lava.
And how do you appease her?
By sacrificing.
Sacrificing what?
Humans.
We didn't always practice
human sacrificing.
There has been a
priest from Tahiti,
who brought the practice in.
His name was Paow
almost 900 years ago.
But it was abolished by
King Kamehameha the second
only a few years ago.
But some are trying
to bring it back.
Who on earth would
try and bring back such
a barbaric practice?
Your Pele sounds like
a very jealous god.
Does it not say
in your holy book
that I am a jealous god?
That only means,
that only means
that we shall have no
other gods before him.
How dare you judge us
when your culture has
the same practice.
I am not judging you.
If I were to judge
you, you would know it.
I would just suggest, we
are not trying to fool you.
So what truly
is your purpose here then?
We spoke with one of
your people in Boston.
He came to us and shared
that there was struggle
and suffering among your people
and our faith moved
us to go forward
and travel 10 months
in hard conditions
on a broken down ship.
We came here to assist you.
To build, to help
you with planting
and caring for the sick.
And for sharing good news.
Good news?
So, the truth comes out.
Over there is your hut.
Kapu, Makana, take them.
Okay, I'm going to
head back to the ship
and I hope they don't have
too much ketchup here.
Why?
Well, to put on you
after they cook you.
Good luck, farewell.
Walk.
I knew that
was why they had come.
Our ancestor Henry Okaheo went
to their land several
years ago and died.
But his spirit brought
back this good news.
It was about their god,
but we already had
gods, many of them.
Why would we need one more?
What would compel them
to travel all this way
to tell us about their one god?
Our enemies have arrived.
This is not good.
Where are they from?
How can you be certain
they are our enemies?
Because they come from the land
that cursed dog Opukahaia went to.
A place called America.
So the
ship is leaving?
Yes, it's
going back to England.
And you and your
friends have stayed behind?
Yes.
What do they want?
What do you think they want?
They want to force us to
worship their God.
The god of Captain Cook?
Yes Captain Cook’s god.
The foreign man brought guns and canons
to our lands and nothing more.
But these people don’t have guns.
To me, it seems they are here to help.
Don’t be a fool Mele!
We must get them off our island.
Let’s ask Pele first.
We don't want to die.
We will not die.
They will die first.
Be careful.
Maybe these foreign people
are some foreign gods?
Never. That’s legend.
I sense fear in them.
Their god has no power.
Their god will not protect them from ME.
What do you mean by that?
Pele is angry, but her
anger will subside.
I'm not talking about Pele.
All due respect, Chiefess,
I'm talking about
the god who created
heaven and earth.
The god through which
all things were made.
Nothing exists without him.
May I introduce
you to Akira Endo.
Nice to meet you.
He is a samurai
warrior from Japan.
My pleasure, how did
you end up here Mr. Endo?
I was the Japanese
ambassador to Holland under
the Tokugawa, but pirates
over took our ship
and I was taken hostage.
Incredible tale, sir.
Where are you from?
America.
Would you look at that,
bloody missionaries.
If they keep this up,
they're gonna convert
the entire bloody island.
Aye, that's right they will.
Well I'm not gonna
let that happen.
Without whiskey, without
rum, without women,
what left is there?
Nothing!
Nothing, it's an outrage!
Let's go, boys.
We are all cursed.
The gods are angry we have
let these foreign people into our land.
They are infidels!
They must die by tomorrow night.
The gods are angry
Kanoa has spoken with Pele
so we know she is right.
They must die by tomorrow night.
No...
Anyone who lays a hand
on them will be put to death.
Then command them to LEAVE, Chiefess
They’re helping us.
I will not force them to leave.
They are our guests.
Chiefess, if the goddess demands it,
we must obey. Let us sacrifice them!
We cannot sacrifice the foreign man.
They are defiled like women.
You know human sacrifice was abolished.
You will not touch anyone
Mere humans cannot abolish
what the great goddess requires.
Our king did.
And he's human.
Besides, he only issued a Kanalaa.
It can be broken, Chiefess.
Kamehameha is Ali’i nui
because he is a descendant of the celestials!
ENOUGH.
I have heard from Pele.
She wants to destroy us all
This man does not
believe in Pele.
Do you, Mr. Thornton?
Answer me.
I believe in god, that's all.
Henry, what is going on, come.
What is going on?
It's all under control.
- Control?
- Yes.
I heard them, they
want to kill us.
That's Kanoa, she
has some kind of a.
This is insanity,
we must leave.
God will protect us, Mary.
How can you be so
sure, Brother Hiram?
Psalm 91.
Words will not stop a spear
from piercing your heart.
God is in control
brother Henry.
Yes, God is in control.
This is insane,
we must leave here.
I'm sorry for
what has happened.
I will do everything in my
power to protect you, but.
But what?
You must be careful.
The priestess Kanoa,
she's very powerful
and she has great
influence on the people.
Shoo, shoo!
The foreign woman.
Shoo!
I don't
know why she came here.
She is so miserable.
Oh, I can't stand it.
- I
- feel sorry for her.
I don't know how much
longer they intend to stay.
Oh Henry, the mosquitoes
are everywhere here.
Yeah, just blame
it on Captain Cook.
KAPU! COME HERE.
Hurry!
Kapu. Approach.
I'm sorry but we must make a
sacrifice to Pele.
Kipa! Nalau!
Take him to the altar!
Alika!
Please don't do this.
Enough.
Take Kapu to the altar -
he will be sacrificed today.
WAIT!
Blame it on Captain Cook.
What, what does that mean?
He brought mosquitoes
to the islands.
Or should I say mosquito larvae.
They were in the water they
brought aboard the ships.
Did he bring anything good?
Yeah, towels, coats.
Good morning, Reverend Henry.
Good morning, Makana.
Miss Mary.
What's going on here?
Our sacrifice has escaped.
What sacrifice?
Kapu.
Why did they choose him?
They claimed he stole from
them, but it's not true.
If Kanoa and Alika get their way
he will be drowned
or sacrificed.
I thought they abandoned
the sacrifice of humans?
We did, but Alika
and Kanoa wish
to return to the
ways of the past.
This is madness.
Mary!
Mary, Mary where are you going?
Stop, stop!
How could you bring me here?
I mean, you wanted to come.
No, you told me that these
were a peaceful loving people.
Well, I hate them.
I hate every last one of these
filthy, worthless savages!
Mary, please.
Your words are
accountable to God.
These filthy, worthless
savages they are
God's creation just like us.
They have a soul just like us.
Why should I care
what God thinks?
God cares nothing for me.
If he cared one wit about
my welfare I would be
in Boston instead of on
this wretched island.
You brought me to this
god forsaken land,
half a world away
from everything
and everyone I have ever loved
and you expect me to be gracious
as they prepare to
sacrifice a man!
How are you going
to share your faith
when you despise them?
If you think that
they want your faith
then you are a fool, Henry.
They want nothing from
you and yet you continue
to try ingratiate
yourself with them.
What is it that you want?
Maybe you'd like one of these
Hawaiian women for yourself?
Oh, my god.
I'm so sorry, Mary.
Please.
God, what have I done?
I hate you.
I curse the day that we met.
You will never lay
a hand on me again.
Mary.
Be careful, Chiefess.
What do you mean?
We don't know what
their intentions are.
They have come to Japan
to force us to trade.
We refused.
And?
They threatened to
take over our country.
Be careful.
Well, how are you on this
fine evening, good sir?
May I help you gentlemen?
Gentlemen!
No gents here, just
us boozing, whoring,
good for nothing
sinners, right preacher?
I'm not here to judge you.
Oh you're not?
What if I did this, huh?
Huh!
Am I a sinner now, huh?
Am I a sinner now?
Stop it.
Stay out of this, old man.
This doesn't concern you.
I said, that's enough.
What, who are you?
Go in peace.
Boys, let's go.
Let's get out of here, come on.
You are not well
received, Mr. Bingham.
I guess not.
So, why are you here?
To tell people about God.
I can't believe you travel
this long a journey for that.
There must be another reason.
Like what?
Like you want to force these
people to trade with you.
I assure you, I have
no such intentions.
Americans came to
Japan to force us
to trade with you, remember?
That's not why I'm here.
I'm here for something
more valuable.
And what is that?
I'm hoping to find out.
Excuse me.
Let's go.
I can't take this....
I did nothing wrong
What a coward
You're such a great warrior
Kapu
You should be honored to
sacrifice yourself
Stop crying!
You filthy coward!
I don't deserve to die!
Oh that poor man.
Chiefess, can't
you do something?
I don't agree with
this, Mrs. Thornton.
But I cannot go against
what the priestesses say
in regards to Pele.
There must be a sacrifice.
But aren't you their leader?
What would happen if they were
not to go through with this?
The volcano might erupt and
completely cover this island.
You truly believe that?
Pele was exiled by her
father because of her anger.
The last straw was between
her and her sister.
Namakaokahai who's
husband Pele had seduced.
Pagan barbarism!
Hiram!
Hiram, what happened?
Nothing, I'm okay.
Did someone attack you?
Yes.
Who?
Who did this to you?
The sailors.
Why does God allow all
of these worthless beasts
to roam the earth?
Mary, we must
love our enemies.
And even pray for those
that persecute us.
Otherwise, what difference
is there between us and them?
Sometimes it is not possible
or practical to
live out God's word.
Mary, keep the faith, Mary.
I have
known Kapu for many years.
He was a good man.
He does not deserve
to die like this.
I watched them put
him on the altar.
I became filled with rage.
What god requires a man to
die for it's appeasement
and if it isn't
appeased will erupt
and destroy more innocent lives?
These foreigners
speak of a just god.
Who is right?
It is a great honor to die
for your god, Kapu.
Pele will be appeased.
Your spirit will be released
so you can be free!
With the sword of Captain Cook
Goddess, we offer this sacrifice to you.
It is a great day!
Pele has been appeased.
What is the matter with all of you?
We are saved!
I know that is wrong.
It is.
I knew Kapu, he
is not a bad man.
I'm sure he wasn't.
Take him to the volcano
as a sacrifice to Pele
And throw him in.
Mary, are you all right?
Mary, please, talk to me.
I can't believe
this is happening.
They sacrificed a human
life just to appease
some pagan god.
Henry, please take me back home.
I don't want to stay here.
We don't belong here, for the
love of God, Henry please.
I should
have said something.
No, no, we can't.
This is their land, not ours.
We can't forget that.
And so two months went by
and we watched these
missionaries from a distance.
Unsure of what to make of them.
They continued to persevere.
Meanwhile, the foreign woman
becomes more frail by the day.
I fear she may not
live much longer she
is so weak and fearful.
Mary, I may never have
said this to you before.
I love you.
I'm so sorry for what
you had to go through
while you're here.
I promise to have you
on the first boat home.
You have my word on this.
I promise, Mary.
Woo!
That was incredible.
You did pretty good
for your first time.
Thank you.
Do you have any
children, Mr. Bingham?
I did.
But my son passed.
And shortly afterwards
my wife died.
We're sorry, Mr. Bingham.
How you overcome such a loss?
God, he helped me through it.
Is the woman doing OK?
She's not adjusting
well, unfortunately.
Is there anything
we can do to help her?
I don't know what
to do, honestly.
Except pray.
You pray, to god?
Yes.
Are you all right, dear?
We're going to
die here, Henry.
No, God will protect us.
If there is a
god, he's not here.
We need to go home.
I will take care of you.
Get me off this savage island.
I made a promise to you
and I'll have you on
the next boat home.
And I'll be with you, I promise.
I'll never leave
your side, I promise.
God help me!
Help me know what
you want me to do.
Oh, I've utterly
failed in everyway.
My wife despises me, Lord.
She'll never forgive me.
God, did you just send
all of us here to die?
It seems neither of
us can sleep tonight.
Uh, no, it's true, it's true.
How is your wife?
She's not well.
I'm afraid she's not well.
I'm sorry to hear that.
Is there anything I can do?
No, no she's being
ferociously attacked by
a terrible, terrible enemy.
Enemy?
Yes.
What enemy?
Satan, the devil.
Ah, yes, the enemy of all.
Tell me something.
Why does our god
require a sacrifice
and yours does not?
There was a human sacrifice
and his name was Jesus Christ.
Wait a minute, you said
this Jesus was God's son.
How did he become
a human sacrifice?
For what reason?
He let himself be killed
as a final sacrifice
to appease the wrath of
God for all of our sins.
Now I'm really confused.
You and Hiram spoke
of this god of love
now he is a god of wrath?
Which one is it?
It's hard to believe in a god
that could have so many
facets to his personality
that he could love his
children, bring the grace
of forgiveness to
the whole world,
and still have such anger against
those who sin against him.
But why would God want
to sacrifice his only son?
Why not an evil person
who deserves it?
Because it was a
perfect sacrifice.
The only acceptable
sacrifice to God.
A god who sacrifices
himself for humans.
That intrigues me.
Have a good night, Mr. Thornton.
Good night, your highness.
Good night, Chiefess.
Father God, please help us.
We came to bring the
good news about your son
to these people but it's been
anything but good for us.
Please dear God, bless my wife.
Help her recover,
if it is your will.
Please dear God.
If it is your will.
The next ship arrives
in less than two weeks.
The missionaries have now been
on our island for three months.
The woman missionary
is doing poorly.
We offered her meat, poi, but
she cannot eat what we eat.
Perhaps their holiday celebration
will lift her spirits.
For you.
Would love to,
thank you, thank you.
Very good, mahalo.
You're welcome.
Mahalo, mahalo.
Chiefess, I understand they will
all leave on the next ship.
Mr. Thornton and his wife will leave,
but Mr. Bingham will stay.
They must all be gone.
I’m the Chiefess of this tribe.
It’s by my orders who may
stay and who must leave.
They are a danger to our tribe.
Like Cook they will attempt
to make everyone forget our gods.
They’re infidels.
How?
They must all be aboard
the next ship.
Kanoa has the entire islands
in the grip of fear.
No one wishes to listen.
Even to possible truth.
Look at all of them.
Look at all the stars.
How many are there?
A billion?
A trillion?
We come here, some of us
away from our families
and our homes.
But to spend
Christmas with others
and any sacrifice for
the sake of Jesus Christ
is rewarded much more.
Reverend Henry, Makana to you.
Merry Christmas.
Oh, thank you, Makana.
And merry Christmas for you.
May I join you guys?
Yes please, it's so
nice to see you came.
Akira, yes?
Can we sing "Silent
Night" for you?
Yes, please.
Bless us with your
beautiful voices, young men.
Ready?
♪ Silent night, holy night ♪
♪ All is calm, all is bright ♪
♪ 'Round yon virgin
mother and child ♪
♪ Holy infant so
tender and mild ♪
♪ Sleep in heavily peace ♪
Well that was beautiful.
Let's sing it again.
♪ Silent night, holy night ♪
The leaders were looking for you.
I was at gathering with
the missionaries.
I don’t understand...
It was unlike anything....
I’ve ever heard...
What happened?
I felt....
Peace
Love
Joy.
What are you saying?
You’re not...
What if...
it really is true?
This God took the form
of a human being and sacrificed
Himself
for the redemption of the entire
world...
That is unfathomable.
Our villager Opukaha’ia believed.
He wrote about this Jesus.
But I didn’t understand.
Chiefess, there will be another
sacrifice in three days.
Who?
Makana
Are you kidding?
No. We must end this.
We cannot Chiefess.
The god Ku demands it.
Do you have no regard for
our King Kamehameha II?
He commanded the end of
human sacrificing.
He ended sacrifice because
of the foreign man
Captain Cook and the British
sailors who wanted our goods.
You want us to stop worshipping
our god?
What if our god is not
what we think he is?
What if there is another path?
You are allowing the foreign man’s
beliefs to infiltrate your mind.
What kind of god requires
a human sacrifice?
Makana is a good man and
we’re going to kill him
because Kanoa commands it?
She is only a woman.
Only a woman?
Kanoa is very powerful.
Do not cross her.
The decision is made.
He will be sacrificed.
God...please...
if you are out there....
I want to know the truth.
Who are you?
Who are you really?
Please show me the truth...
I NEED to know!!
I cannot go on like this!
If you exist, show me!
Show me!
Mary, Mary this is the freshest
food you will ever find.
Much fresher than in Boston.
And look here, they were just.
They gave you a gift.
I'm so sorry what you're
going through here.
Merry Christmas, Mary.
Merry Christmas.
Is she okay, Hiram?
She's suffering from
some sort of break down.
I don't know what
to do, honestly.
Henry is with her now.
Well, what about prayer?
Yes.
Prayer.
Deep prayer.
He who dwells in the
secret place of the most high
shall abide under the
shadow of the almighty.
I will say of the
Lord, he is my refuge
and my fortress, my God.
In him I will trust.
Surely he shall deliver
you from the snare
of the foul and from
the perilous pestilence.
He shall cover you
with his feathers
and under his wings
you shall take refuge.
His truth shall be your
shield and buckler.
You shall not be afraid
of the terror by night
nor of the arrow
that flies by day.
Nor of the pestilence
that walks in darkness.
Nor of the destruction that
lays waste at noon day.
A 1,000 may fall at your side
and 10,000 at your right hand
but it shall not come near you.
Only with your
eyes shall you look
and see the reward of the wicked
because you have made the
Lord who is my refuge,
even the most high,
your dwelling place.
No evil shall befall you.
Did you want to see me?
I have heard some
distressing news.
What?
Has Chiefess Kapiolani
accepted this new God?
I don’t know the answer
to that question.
Don’t lie to me!
Pele punishes ALL liars!
She loves and respects
Pele, you know that.
We will get it out of her.
Pray to Pele it’s not true.
Gather the elders and
other priestesses.
Henry.
Heave, heave, heave!
Heave, give it all
you've got, heave!
Heave!
Give it all you've
got, heave, heave!
Come on, come on.
I'm so happy you survived.
Mary, Mary are you okay?
Yes.
Huh?
I'm just glad he survived.
Oh me too, me too.
I'm so sorry.
I've behaved so terribly.
I made a fool of myself
and I brought shame
on our entire group.
No, you didn't, Mary.
I can see it in their eyes.
You were so brave to come here
in the first place.
I should have seen,
before we came,
how difficult it
would be here for you.
Oh Mary, I'm so proud.
I'm so proud of you.
Thank you, thank you.
And just like
that Mary became a new person.
The heavy veil of
oppression lifted from her.
It was the beginning
of a new day.
So beautiful.
Yes, it is so beautiful.
I was talking about you.
Me, Henry.
You find me beautiful?
Yes.
Stay strong my brothers.
Our god demands a sacrifice...
we’ve picked a man
This man fulfills the
requirements of Pele.
We have picked Makana.
What's going on?
They are sacrificing
another of us.
Again?
Who?
Makana.
Why?
Because his father
was an enemy of our king.
God give us strength.
I’m sorry brother.
You have been chosen.
Your father served King Kalikele
and therefore was an enemy
You would have me pay
for the sins of my father?
I’m sorry.
You will be sacrificed
tomorrow morning
to Ku and Pele.
This is madness.
Utter madness!
Hiram, what's wrong?
They're sacrificing again.
A human?
Yes, Makana.
Not Makana, this can't be.
We have to stop this.
I don't know how we can.
I pity you Makana.
You should have gone
like a man.
Henry always says
that we shouldn't interfere.
Look what good
that did last time.
I'm not gonna stand by and watch
an innocent man be put to death.
It's only one of you, Hiram,
with no weapons against
all of these warriors.
I'm sorry, Mary.
I have to try.
Makana is my friend, my brother!
He's our friend, too
but I'm afraid there's
nothing you can do.
I'm sorry, Mary.
I have to try.
The gods are not happy.
Let him go.
We captured him.
He will be sacrificed.
You do not lead this tribe,
Alika.
I answer to Pele and Ku.
They require a human sacrifice.
Kanoa said-
-Kanoa does not lead our tribe.
I will not tolerate our
gods being defiled.
Our entire village could die
if we do not appease them.
Look up
the volcano is already angry.
I am trying to save our
village from destruction.
If you care about your people,
you will hold your tongue
against me
Are you gonna let
them sacrifice Makana?
What choice do I
have, Mr. Bingham?
I cannot go against
what Pele asks.
Tell them to stop.
But it is up to the gods.
Alika says ‘no one’ may enter.
Under strict orders
I am your Chiefess
I command you let him in.
Be quick, Hiram.
Yes, Chiefess.
How are you Makana, my brother?
I'm so sorry for the trouble
we got you in, my friend.
I am to die tomorrow.
I need to know the
truth about your god.
He's not my god.
He's everyone's god.
He can be your god too.
It's too late now.
It's never too late.
As long as there is
breath in your body
the Bible says he who
calls upon the Lord
will be saved.
Is it possible?
Yes.
It is a wonderful
thing for a god
to sacrifice himself for us.
Brother Hiram, please,
my wife and children.
Make sure they are
taken care of, please.
Yes, of course I will.
What I wouldn't give
to go surfing again.
It is time, Makana!
What is this?
Where is Makana?
I am taking his place.
I said, I am taking his place.
You can sacrifice me instead.
Why is Hiram with them?
He must have done
something wrong.
Hiram,
what are you doing?
What is going on?
What's going on?
Stay back!
Alika!
Don't do this
GET OUT!
Why are you
holding Mr. Bingham?
He said he would
be sacrificed.
What?
What, no!
I don't have a
family, Makana does.
Hiram, this is not our affair!
Hiram this is
madness, please tell them no.
♪ Holy night ♪
♪ All is calm, all is bright ♪
♪ 'Round yon virgin,
mother and child ♪
♪ Holy infant so
tender and mild ♪
♪ Sleep in heavenly peace ♪
♪ Silent night, holy night ♪
♪ Shepherds quake at the sight ♪
♪ Glories stream
from heaven afar ♪
Hiram, don't!
Please, don't!
What are you doing?
We cannot wait another minute!
Henry, do something!
Chiefess, please.
He must be sacrificed!
STOP!
PUT YOUR KNIFE DOWN!
I SAID STOP!
People!
Listen to me!
Give me your ears!
I have been your Chiefess
for two years.
You know I have served
you faithfully and with integrity.
Everything I have done
has always been for
the good of the community.
We should never be afraid
of the truth. No matter how it hurts.
I’ve made a decision.
You no longer have to
worship Pele.
You have the freedom to
worship
whomever you choose.
What are you saying?
You heard me.
They may choose to worship
whomever they want.
PELE WILL KILL US ALL
FOR YOUR INSOLENT WORDS!
She will rain fire and
brimstone on us
How dare you speak
against her
I believe God is bigger
You don’t believe in Pele
anymore?
No.
Is she not also a foreign
deity from Borabora?
Chiefess, have you lost
your mind?
You are still free to worship
your god.
Prove your God is real.
How?
Go to the volcano
and see if Pele will
allow you to live.
I shall do that tomorrow,
when the sun rises.
In the meantime, release
Mr. Bingham to me.
Oh thank
god, thank god.
Come, come.
You're safe now,
you're safe now.
Hiram,
please, please, Hiram.
Once Kapiolani dies tomorrow
morning
kill the foreigners
Which ones?
All of them.
Let's make sure no one
comes to our island again
Is this necessary?
Just send them back
to their country.
You DARE to challenge me
Alika?
No
You are the only one
that wants them dead.
So what?
When Kapiolani dies,
I will then become your Chiefess.
Pele will be merciful to us
after Kapiolani is gone
You aren’t really doing this
to appease Pele are you?
What do you mean?
This is about power.
You want to be the Chiefess.
Don't you ever speak that
way to me again
You must leave now
before the villagers arise.
I have a boat waiting
to take you to Oahu.
Why?
If I do not return
you will be killed.
You will return.
Either way you should leave.
If we leave now then
our faith means nothing.
The priestesses,
they're very powerful.
They may have us killed
before this all plays out.
No one has ever returned
from the volcano.
Sweetie, that was so
beautiful, you were wonderful.
Yeah.
It's a good boy.
- Come here.
- Good boy.
Listen, she's arranged for us
to leave tomorrow
morning on a boat.
Why?
Because they're gonna kill
us if she does not come back.
I believe she will return.
No, I know, but
we can't be certain.
I'm not concerned about myself
but I cannot let
anything happen to you.
I am not afraid to die
as long as I am with you.
Good, thank god.
I know, I know.
It will be all right,
we're in God's hands.
Just come with me, come on.
Okay, come on.
Jesus, I love you.
I know you are the son of God.
I know you are the
savior of the world.
Please be with me as
I go to the volcano.
And if I die, I look
forward to seeing you.
Farewell.
I am going but I
will be back.
Don’t be a fool, Chiefess
I'm asking you not
to do this
We have had our differences
but I don’t want you to
sacrifice yourself.
We beg of you
not to do such a foolish
thing.
Chiefess, you have been
good to all of us!
If you do this,
you will never come back.
What was lost shall be found.
All of the prophecies say
you will die
if you go to the Halema’uma’u
without a sacrifice.
Then I shall die.
Shame on you.
You are an infidel like them.
No one touches
them while I am gone.
That is a direct order.
They will be unharmed.
But if you do not return
by the end of the
day, they will die.
Leave them be.
Alika, it is me that you want.
Kapiolani, I am
willing to die today.
We will kill you both!
Will she be safe?
Yes.
Should I accompany her?
No.
I have heard that no
one ever comes back alive.
She's in God's hands now.
You will stay, why?
You knew the
consequences if I fail.
We won't desert you.
Your faith is our faith.
You're our sister in Christ.
We will stand with
you until death.
You are truly my
brothers and sisters then.
- Yes.
Yes, we are one family now.
Chiefess, please.
Please forgive me.
I behaved so despicably
when I first arrived here.
I treated you with
such contempt.
I was a poor example of
a Christian and a woman.
And yet you embraced our faith.
I know now that I am no
better than anyone here
on this island and
in fact far worse
than you with your
extraordinary courage.
I know you do not have
any reason to forgive me
but please understand that
my bigotry was only mine.
It had nothing to do with them.
Please forgive them,
please forgive all of us.
Mary, we have
all been lost once.
But now we are found.
We are all children of our God.
Be at peace, my sister.
I love you.
I love you, too, courage.
The Lord is my shepherd
I shall not want.
He maketh me to lie
down in green pastures.
He leadeth me beside
the still waters.
He restoreth my soul.
He leadeth me in the
paths of righteousness
for his namesake.
Ye, though I walk
through the valley
of the shadow of death,
I will fear no evil
for thou art with me.
Thy rod and thy staff,
they comfort me.
Thou preparest a table before me
in the presence of my name.
Thou anointest my head with
oil, my cup runeth over.
Surely, goodness and
mercy shall follow me all
the days of my life
and I will dwell
in the house of the Lord.
God is with us.
God be with her.
Prove yourself, show yourself!
Prove yourself to me.
Are you asleep?
Take cover!
Kill them, kill them!
Kill them all!
All of them?
Yes!
He who dwells in the secret
place of the most high.
I will sayeth the Lord, he
is my refuge and my strength.
In him I trust.
It is unfortunate it
had to come to this.
You have sung great chords.
But we must follow orders.
Prepare to die!
Is she going into the volcano?
Impossible....
Are you sure?
She wants all of us to die!
WAIT! She's coming out!
She's alive, she's alive.
She's alive.
Let them go.
They are free to worship the
volcano god if they choose
and we are free to
worship our god.
The truth shall set you free.
You can worship
any god you choose.
As for me and my
household, we will serve
the Lord Jesus Christ.
There will be no more
killing, no more sacrifices.
No more religion.
You are set free
from this bondage.
No!
Enough!
Did you hear?
There will be no more killing.
This is our Chiefess and you
will obey her command, go!
Mahalo.
I am sorry I misjudged you.
My allegiance is to Pele
but perhaps I will consider
your god too
That was the most courageous
act that I've ever seen.
It was not my doing,
I was led by God.
It was a miracle.
We were afraid you
wouldn't come back.
I had my doubts.
It is a cause for celebration.
Who are you?
A man, just like you.
It
was a cause for celebration.
I felt something on that
mountain I cannot describe.
A hand of someone
who protected me.
And so it was, I
finally understood what
the good news meant.
We found a new freedom
we hadn't known
and a god who deeply loved us.
People tell me what
a courageous act
it was to challenge the volcano
but it was courage born
from the love of God.
The love I had been
searching for all my life.